Guide to the Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, 11th century - 17th century
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection
11th century - 17th century
Vassar College. Library
22 codices, 78 leaves and cuttings (3 boxes, 2 map folders)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Codices, leaves, and fragments of manuscripts and illuminated manuscripts, primarily in Latin, deriving largely from religious work such as psalters, books of hours, and sermons. Also includes scholarly and literary works.
Scope and Content Note
Codices, leaves, and fragments of manuscripts and illuminated manuscripts, primarily in Latin, deriving largely from religious work such as psalters, books of hours, and sermons. Also includes scholarly and literary works.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The English Documents Collection includes items dating from 1552 on.
The Nicholas B. Scheetz Collection includes manuscript material dating from the 9th to 18th centuries.
Separated Materials
Series II. Leaves and Clippings - Items 51, 70, and 73 were separated from the collection and added to the Middle Eastern Manuscripts Collection, January 2024.
Series II. Leaves and Clippings - Items 71 and 72 were separated from the collection and added to the Russian Leaves Collection, January 2024.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Catholic Church--Prayers and devotions
Subjects:
Bible; Books of Hours; Illumination of books and manuscripts, Armenian; Illumination of books and manuscripts, European; Illumination of books and manuscripts, Medieval; Manuscripts, Armenian; Manuscripts, Latin; Manuscripts, Medieval; Music--Manuscripts; Psalters; Sermons, Latin
Document Types:
Books of hours; Illuminated manuscripts; Psalters; Sermons
VCL Categories:
Medieval and Early Modern Manuscripts
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, April 2007.
Updated by Mark Seidl, October 2011, September 2014, and April 2019.
Updated by Emma Gronbeck, March 2023 and January 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gifts and transfers from a variety of sources.
Item 74 was purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., February 2011. [M2011-006]
Item 83 was the bequest of Frederich Hammond, November 2023. [M2024-004]
Series List
- Series I. Codices, 14th century - 17th century
  Arrangement
  Codices are arranged according to MS number.
- Series II. Leaves and Cuttings, 11th century - 17th century
  Leaves and cuttings are arranged according to item number.
Container List
- Series I. Codices
  - [See Series II. Leaves and Cuttings, Item 54] (MS 1)
  - Vergil, Georgics [Italy (Florence?), 15th century (1st half?) (MS 2)
  - Compendium including works attributed to Bonaventura, Hugh of St. Victor, and Anselm [Northern Italy (Veneto or Emilia)], 15th century (first half or middle) (MS 3)
  - Psalter, illuminated by Jean Semont [Franco-Flemish border area (Tournai)], circa 1390-1400 (MS 4)
  - Book of Hours, Use of Rome [Italy (Florence?)], [circa 1480?]; (Missing) (MS 5)
  - Book of Hours, Use of Paris, in Latin and French [France (Paris)], circa 1475 (MS 6)
  - Book of Hours, Use of Amiens, in Latin and French [France (Amiens)], circa 1480 (MS 7)
  - Book of Hours, Use of Rome [Germany (or Switzerland?)], late 15th century; (Missing) (MS 8)
  - Book of Hours, Use of Besançon, in Latin and French [France (Lyon?)], circa 1425-1450 (MS 9)
  - Pope Adrian VI, Bull “In cena domini”, on paper [Germany (Bamberg area?)], 1527 (or 1523 with additions?) (MS 10)
  - Book of Hours, Use of Mons(?), in Latin and French [France-Netherlands border region (Hainault)], mid-15th century (MS 11)
  - Jerome of Mondsee (Johannes de Werdea) (d. 1475), et al.(?), Sermons [Austria (Behamberg?)], 1474 (MS 12)
  - [See Series II. Leaves and Cuttings, Item 61] (MS 13)
  - [See Series II. Leaves and Cuttings, Items 62-67] (MS 14)
  - Inventories, mainly of Livestock and Furnishings, in English [England], 1549-1557 (MS 15)
  - Gradual, Cistercian Use, Temporale, Winter Part [Spain], 16th century (early) (MS 16)
  - "Ferial Psalter, Secular Use, for the Night Offices from Wednesday to Saturday [Spain]", [17th century?] (MS 17)
  - "Manorial Accounts for Uggeshall, Sotterley, Ellough, and Willingham, in Latin with insertions in English [England (Suffolk)]", 1553-1599 (MS 18)
  - Portable Breviary, Franciscan Use, adapted for Augustinian Use [Northern Italy (Genoa?)], 14th century (2nd quarter?, after 1317); with 15th century additions (MS 19)
  - Cicero, De Senectute, Paradoxa, Somnium Scipio [Italy], 15th century (MS 20)
  - Hauprecht Zapff, Compilation of Excerpts from Sebastian Franck’s Chronica, in German [Southern Moravia (Nové Mlýny)], circa 1595/6 (MS 21)
  - Commendations of Souls [Germany], 15th century, with 18th/19th century addition (MS 22)
  - Chronicle of Kings of Rome, etc., in Italian, on paper [Italy (Tuscany?, Florence?)], 16th century (between 1534 and 1549) (MS 23)
  - Dominican Ferial Psalter [Southern Germany, Austria, or Switzerland], 15th century (between 1455 and circa 1461) (MS 24)
  - Privileges du Vicomte de Turenne [France], 1523 Feb 3 (MS 25)
- Series II. Leaves and Cuttings
  - Two Leaves from a Decorated Pocket Bible [England (or perhaps France)], 13th century [third quarter?] (Box Box 1,, Item Items 1-2)
  - A Fragment of a Glossed Psalms [France or England], late 12th or early 13th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 3)
  - A Fragmentary Leaf, Apparently from a List of Aphorisms Set to Music [Germany], 11th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 4)
  - A Leaf from Philip the Chancellor (d. 1236), Sermons [France (Paris?)], 13th century (middle or second half) (Box Box 1,, Item Item 5)
  - A Leaf from Thomas Aquinas, Commentary on the Sentences of Peter Lombard [Italy (Florence)], circa 1450-1499 (Box Box 1,, Item Item 6)
  - A Leaf from a Book of Hours, in Latin with French rubrics, with miniatures of St. Francis and St. Lawrence [France], circa 1475–1485 (Box Box 1,, Item Item 7)
  - A Leaf from a Processional(?) [France (Normandy?, Caen?)], 15th century; [See also Nicholas B. Scheetz Collection, MS 11a-c ] (Box Box 1,, Item Item 8)
  - A Leaf from a Gradual [France], 16th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 9)
  - A Leaf from a Breviary [Italy (Tuscany, in or near Lucca)], 1464 (Box Box 1,, Item Items 10, 37)
  - A Leaf from a Praxapostolos, in Armenian, 15th or 16th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 11)
  - Two Leaves from a Breviary, Use of Sarum(?) [France (Rouen?)], circa 1400-1450 (Box Box 1,, Item Items 12-13)
  - Two Leaves from a Book of Hours, Use of Troyes [France], mid-15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Items 14-15)
  - A Leaf from a Book of Hours, in Netherlandish [Northern Netherlands], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 16)
  - Three Leaves from a Book of Hours, Use of Paris [France (Paris?)], circa 1475 (Box Box 1,, Item Items 17-19)
  - A Leaf from a Book of Hours [France], early 16th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 20)
  - A Leaf from a Book of Hours [France], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 21)
  - A Leaf from a miniature Book of Hours [France?], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 22)
  - Two leaves from a Book of Hours, with rubrics in Netherlandish [Southern Netherlands (Bruges?)], [mid?]-15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Items 23-24)
  - Five Leaves with Miniatures from the Calendar of a Book of Hours [France (Reims, or Paris?)], early 16th (or late 15th) century] (Box Box 1,, Item Items 25-29)
  - A Leaf from the Chichester “Evangelia Festivalia” [England (Chichester?)], early 16th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 30)
  - A Grant of property, in Latin with some Words in Middle English [England (Kent)], [1425 or 1426] Jan 16 (Box Box 1,, Item Item 31)
  - A Leaf from a Processional, on paper [Italy], 16th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 32)
  - A Leaf from the Litany in a Book of Hours [France], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 33)
  - A Leaf from a Burial Service [Italy], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 34)
  - Two Leaves from a Book of Hours [France], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Items 35-36)
  - A Leaf from a Breviary [France (Paris?)], circa 1300/1350 (Box Box 1,, Item Item 38)
  - A Miniature Depicting The Betrayal and Arrest of Christ, doubtless from a Book of Hours [Southern Netherlands (Flanders, Ghent?)], circa 1450-1475 (Box Box 1,, Item Item 39)
  - Two Miniatures each depicting a Pope Performing Mass, Cut from a Missal of Pope Leo X [Italy (Florence)], circa 1513-1521 (Box Box 1,, Item Items 40-41)
  - A Miniature by the Spanish Forger, on a Cutting from an Antiphonary [Italy, 14th century; and France, late 19th or early 20th century], 14th century, late 19th or early 20th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 42)
  - A Leaf from a Missal [Italy], 15th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 43)
  - A Leaf from a Bible [Bohemia], 15th century (Box Box 2,, Item Item 44)
  - A Leaf of a Martyrology [Italy], 12th century ([3rd?] quarter) (Box Box 2,, Item Item 45)
  - A Leaf from a Psalter [Southern Netherlands (Bruges?)], circa 1200-1250 (Box Box 2,, Item Item 46)
  - A Leaf from a folio-sized Bible [France (Paris?)], circa 1220-1240 (Box Box 2,, Item Item 47)
  - A Leaf from “The Bohun Bible” [England (East Anglia, perhaps Cambridge?)], mid-14th century (Box Box 2,, Item Item 48)
  - Two Leaves from a Palimpsest Antiphonary [Italy], [14th?] and 15th century (Box Box 2,, Item Items 49-50)
  - [See Middle Eastern Manuscripts Collection, Item 1 ] (Box Box 2,, Item Item 51)
  - Two Leaves from a Homilary, in Armenian [Iran (Isfahan)], 1671–1672; [See also Nicholas B. Scheetz Collection, MS 29a-e ] (Box Box 2,, Item Items 52-53)
  - A Leaf from Virgil, Aeneid [Italy], 14th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 54)
  - A Leaf of a Gradual [Italy], 14th century (Box Box 2,, Item Item 55)
  - A Leaf from a Carthusian(?) Hymnal [Bohemia?], [15th century?] (Box Box 2,, Item Item 56)
  - A Leaf from a Dominican Missal [Italy (Perugia)], 14th century (perhaps 1353) (Box Box 2,, Item Item 57)
  - A Leaf from a Missal [Italy], 15th century (Box Box 2,, Item Item 58)
  - A Leaf from a Breviary, Use of Sarum [England], 14th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 59)
  - A Leaf from Vincent of Beauvais, Speculum Historiale [France (Paris?)], late 14th or early 15th century (Box Box 2,, Item Item 60)
  - A Leaf from Terence, Comedies [Italy (Florence)], circa 1450-1460 (Box Box 2,, Item Item 61)
  - Fragments from Justinian, Institutes, Glossed [Italy (Bologna)], 13th century (Box Box 2,, Item Items 62-67)
  - A Vast Leaf from an Antiphonary [Spain], 16th century (Box Map Case,, Item Item 68)
  - A Vast Leaf from an Antiphonary [Spain], 16th century (Box Map Case,, Item Item 69)
  - [See Middle Eastern Manuscripts Collection, Item 9 ] (Box Box 2,, Item Item 70)
  - [See Russian Leaves Collection, Items 1-2 ] (Box Box 2,, Item Items 71-72)
  - [See Middle Eastern Manuscripts Collection, Item 8 ] (Box Box 2,, Item Item 73)
  - A Leaf from Pseudo-Virgil, in Italian and Latin, on paper [Italy], early 16th century (Box Box 1,, Item Item 74)
  - A Leaf from an Antiphonary [Netherlands (Meuse region?)], early 16th century (Box Box 3 (Oversize),, Item Item 75)
  - A Leaf from an Antiphonary [Germany (Upper Rhine) or Switzerland], circa 1300-1350 (Box Box 3 (Oversize),, Item Item 76)
  - Two Leaves from a Stenciled Gradual [Spain?], [17th century?] (Box Box 3 (Oversize),, Item Items 77-78)
  - Psalms 148–150 [Germany (Cologne?)], 15th century (Box Box 2,, Item Items 79-81)
  - A Leaf from a Psalter [Flanders], circa 1200-1250 (Box Box 2,, Item Item 82)
  - A Bifolium from a Noted Missal [Italy], 15th century (Box Box 2,, Item Item 83)